Finding Aid for Henderson House (University of Michigan) records, 1945-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Henderson House (University of Michigan) records 1945-2010
Henderson House (University of Michigan)
04118 Bimu 2
Women's cooperative dormitory established in 1945 to provide affordable housing and a supportive community for women enrolled in the University of Michigan. The Henderson House records document the administration, activities, cooperative living experience, and history of the house and students who have lived in it. Records include minutes of governing bodies, policies, scrapbooks, and resident applications.
4.75 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record s were received in May 2003 (donor no. 9343 ).
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The Henderson House records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The Henderson House record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Student Academic Records -- Boxes 4-5
Henderson House is an all women's cooperative dormitory opened in 1945 as a result of an idea originally conceived by the Alumnae Council in 1917. The idea was to have a residence for women who would not otherwise be able to attend the University of Michigan without some financial assistance. The first house, called the Alumnae House and later Mary Markley House, was on Washtenaw Avenue. It was the first cooperative house on campus. The Alumnae Council turned Markley House over to the university in 1920.
In 1930 the Alumnae Council purchased property on Observatory for another woman's co-op. The Depression, and then World War II, put plans for the Henderson House on hold, but the Alumnae council continued to raise money to develop the property for the Henderson House. The university eventually decided that it needed the Observatory property to build a new dormitory (now Alice Lloyd Hall). Plans for the Observatory site had already been completed before the War, so in compensation to the Alumnae Council the Board of Regents contributed money to the purchase of a house at 1330 Hill Street, where Henderson House stands today.
Henderson House was named after Mary Bartron Henderson, a 1904 Michigan graduate who was active for many years in Alumnae circles and served as the Executive Secretary of the Alumnae council from 1926 to 1931. She was also one of the driving forces behind the construction and establishment of the Michigan League. At the time of her death, Ms. Henderson was researching cooperative housing for women as a way for students to keeps housing costs to a minimum by doing their own housekeeping. In 1938 the Board of Regents approved a plan to establish a university account for the Henderson Memorial Fund. The stated purpose was "to provide a residence for young women of intelligence and character who desire a college education, but have limited means."
The house itself is a red brick Colonial Revival built in 1892 for a cigar wholesaler named Oscar Robertson. It was later the home of anatomy professor and Dean of the Graduate School, G. Carl Huber. Dr. Huber died in 1934 but his family continued to live in the house until the Council purchased the house. There were plans to renovate the house before opening it, but due to the influx of students at the end of the War, the Henderson Memorial House opened with after some minor remodeling. It housed 15 female students. It operated this way for five years until more major remodeling could take place. The house could then accommodate up to 25 women.
Residents were required to work a predetermined number of hours per semester on various chores around the house, including cooking, cleaning, and other housekeeping duties. This kept the cost of room and board down to a very affordable level. This system continues to be the basis of the functioning of the Henderson House.
In 1950 a library/study wing named after Dean of Women Alice Crocker Lloyd was approved for addition to the Henderson House. However, this was not completed until 1961. A house director's suite was also added on the first floor, the dining room was enlarged, and the kitchen facilities were improved. Six more rooms were added in what had been the attic. This brought the total rooms available to 14, providing space for 29 women.
No major renovations were made to the Henderson House until 1991. The condition of the house had deteriorated since the last major renovation in 1961. The kitchen was renovated along with first floor living areas, and the colors of the linens, paint, upholstery, carpets, and dishes were coordinated for the first time. An ongoing schedule for periodic maintenance was established. House valuables were cataloged and put in the remodeled dining room. In August 1994, the fiftieth-anniversary of Henderson House was celebrated with a three-day event. The Society of Henderson Women was founded at this time to allow former residents to keep abreast of Henderson House events and projects.
Today Henderson House is home to 30 women. Henderson House is open to all female undergraduate and graduate students who demonstrate financial need, academic excellence, and who are willing to participate in a cooperative living environment. Interested students must apply for admission to the Resident Director. It is a three-story house with the upper two floors consisting of sixteen bedrooms (fifteen doubles and two singles). It closely resembles a large family home with shared common quarters, a living room, dining room, library, kitchen, study, and other workrooms. A Resident Director supervises the activities and duties of the house and lives in her own suite in the house. The Resident Director is assisted by a House Manager, a Food Manager, President, Vice President and several other House officers chosen form the current residents living at the House.
A Board of Governors appointed by the Regents governs the House. This board is representative of various alumnae groups. Although the university owns the property, it operates independently of the dormitory system. Because work activities are shared, only room and board is collected from the women at a rate which is considerably less than that of the dormitories. This included three meals per day, which are prepared by the residents and enjoyed together family-style.
As part of its mission to provide affordable housing for female students at Michigan, the Henderson House awards scholarships annually. Nominees are referred to the Alumnae Council Scholarship Committee for scholarships offered by the council and various other clubs. Three scholarships are awarded through the Board of Governors: Daisy Murfin Scholarship, Claire W. Sanders Scholarship, and the Julia Emanuel Scholarship. The Daisy Murfin Scholarship was established in 1950 and the first award was given in 1955. The Clair W. Sanders scholarship was established in 1955 to honor Ms. Sander's many contributions to the establishment of the Henderson House. She graduated from the University of Michigan in 1904 and became the Chief Probation Officer of the Detroit Juvenile Court. She, along with Ms. Henderson, was instrumental in raising the money to build the Michigan League as well as the Henderson House. The Julia Emanuel Fund was begun 1965 and named after the only woman to graduate from Michigan's School of Pharmacy in 1889.
Changes over the last 50 years in the role of women and the college experience are reflected in the history of the Henderson House. Rules governing the coming and going of residents, visitors of the opposite sex, dress codes, and dining protocols have changed over the years reflecting a general loosening of such rules and expectations in the larger society as a whole. The history of Henderson House also reflects the changes in race relations that have occurred since 1945. A survey of Henderson House residents conducted in 1956 asked residents "How would you feel about having negroes (sic.), foreign students, etc. living in the House?" While the response was overwhelmingly in the affirmative to allow such students in the house, there were still a few reservations. This was an issue that the entire nations was dealing with at the time, and in many ways the women of the Henderson House were ahead of the curve.
As gender roles and expectations changed through the 1960s and 1970s, the Henderson House sometimes experienced trouble filling all the available rooms. This has fluctuated over the years but in the last decade, due to increased outreach and publicity, the house has experienced increased interest and is filled most semesters.
House evaluations conducted over the years also show that the more things change the more they stay the same for students living in a coop. Complaints about chores not getting done, others not carrying their fair share of the work load, and personality clashes are evident in the evaluations and meeting minutes throughout the history of the house. Overall, the Henderson House seems to have been (and continues to be) a successfully operated coop with a unique atmosphere and dedicated students. It remains one of the less expensive alternatives to residence hall and apartment living at the University of Michigan.
The records of Henderson House document the administration, activities, cooperative living experience, and history of the house and students who have lived there since its founding in 1945. The record group is divided into four series: Administration and Governance, Activities, Visual Materials, and Resident Applications.
Subjects:
Henderson House (University of Michigan); Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Dormitories--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Alumnae Council.; University of Michigan--Student housing.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Administration and Governance
  The Administration and Governance series, (1945-2010, 2.0 linear feet) contains materials produced in the course of cooperatively running Henderson House. Researchers can find business records, minutes of meetings, documentation regarding the history of the house, and other administrative records. The bulk of the materials consist of minutes and agendas of Henderson House meetings, Board of Governors meetings, and Alumnae Council meetings from 1945 to 2002 and are arranged chronologically. Five ledger books containing minutes from 1946 to 1956 are also part of this series. Other materials found in this series are applications for house officer positions, budget reports, fundraising information, Alumnae Council records, rosters of the Board of Governors, inventories of items in the house, house maintenance files (including floor plans and blueprints), house policies and procedures (including constitutions and by-laws), information regarding relations with the University of Michigan, Resident Director information, scholarship information, surveys of attitudes and experiences, and materials relating to the Society of Henderson Women.
  - Alumni Council Correspondence 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - Application Forms (Blank) 1969-1998 (Box 1)
  - Birthday Greeting 1991-2001 (Box 1)
  - Board of Governors Correspondence 1960-2005 (Box 1)
  - Board of Governors Member Lists 1945-2007 (Box 1)
  - Constitution (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1940-1975 (Box 1)
  - Finances
    - General 1972-2007, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Cash Book 1945-1969 (Outsize Volume) (Box 1)
    - Register 1956-1968 (Box 1)
  - Floor Plans (Box 1)
  - History 1917-1998, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - House Maintenance and Inventories 1947-2000, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - House Meeting Minutes 1957-1960, 2005-2010, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - House Policies and Procedures 1945-2007, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - House Rosters 1946-2007, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Master List of Residents 1946-2000, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 24 folders
    - 1945-1971, 6 folders (Box 1)
    - 1972-2005, 18 folders (Box 2)
    - Executive Meetings 1946-1963 (Box 2)
    - Board of Governors Meetings
      - 1946-1956 (Box 2)
      - 1956-1966 (Box 3)
  - Relations with the University of Michigan 1953-1984 (Box 3)
  - Resident Director 1989-2005 (Box 3)
  - Resident Director's Manual 1977-1978 (Box 3)
  - Resident Evaluations (Survey of Attitudes and Experiences) 1956, 1992-2005, 2008, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Scholarships 1952-1997, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Society of Henderson Women 1998-2000 (Box 3)
- Activities
  The Activities series (1946-2009, 0.4 linear feet) contains materials covering a broad range of activities conducted by the residents of Henderson House over the years, including photographs, two scrapbooks assembled by house residents, and a VHS videocassette. Other folders document things such as publicity, graduation brunch, work parties, 25th Anniversary events, and house recipes. The videocassette is from the Henderson House 50th Anniversary event on August 27, 1994.
  - Graduation Brunch (Box 3)
  - House Recipes and Cookbooks (Box 3)
  - Open House 1988, 1994 (Box 3)
  - Publicity 1967-2009 (Box 3)
  - Work Party 2000 (Box 3)
  - 25th Anniversary 1970 (Box 3)
- Visual Material
  The Visual Materials series contains a range of media that document the residents and their experiences living in the house. Two scrapbooks span the years between 1945-1958. They have small photographs, announcements, newspaper clippings, and other varied ephemera relating to the residents and the activities that they organized and attended. While the photographs within the scrapbooks are in good condition, they are not consistently labeled. This also goes for the individual folder of photographs within the visual materials series. These photographs, while not labeled, appear to document residential life around the early to mid 1990s, with a few pictures from earlier years.
  - Photographs (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook 1945-1949 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook 1957-1958 (Box 3)
  - Slides 1985-1986 (Box 3)
  - VHS Videotape, 50th Reunion 1994 (Box 3)
- Resident Applications 1945-2008
  The Resident Applications series (1946-2001, 1.5 linear feet) contains completed applications for women wanting to live in Henderson House. Because many of these applications contain personally identifiable student educational information they are restricted for 75 years from the date of creation. The applications have been retained for the unique window they offer on the lives of women students at the university. The changing nature of the applications across time reflects shifting values. In addition to biographical information on the students and their families, the forms elicit information on interests, hobbies, as well as assessments on personal habits relative to roommate matching. Early applications include responses to questions such as physical health, vocational preferences, and experience with housework and home management. The forms also ask for written responses to adaptability to cooperative living. Over time, the applications ask variations about what aspect of Henderson House is appealing. More recent applications ask applicants to assess their strengths and weaknesses as co-op members. Personal expense budgets and economic background are also elements of the applications, although the information is solicited differently across time. Overall, the applications will yield interesting qualitative and quantitative data for future research. The applications are arranged first alphabetically for the period 1946 to 1985, and then chronologically. This series also contains applications for various officer positions in the House.
  - Applicants
    - A-Z 1945-1985, 23 folders (Box 4)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2060 ]
    - 1985/1986-1993, 17 folders (Box 4)
    - 1994/1995-2000/2001, 17 folders (Box 5)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2076 ]
    - 2001/2002 (Box 5)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2077 ]
    - 2002/2003 (Box 5)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2078 ]
    - 2002-2004 (Box 5)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2079 ]
    - 2003-2005 (Box 5)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2080 ]
    - 2006-2002 (Box 5)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2083 ]
  - Officer Applicants 1956-1996, 2 folders (Box 5)
    [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2071 ]